Guide to the Aaron Louis Fessler papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Aaron Louis Fessler Papers,
1959-1978.
Fessler, Aaron Louis, 1917-1981.
ca. 550 (1 box)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
4078755
Biographical Note
Librarian. Fessler was Chief Librarian for the Olin Mathiessen Chemical Corporation Library, 1961-1965. His special interest was the information storage and retrieval of scientific literature.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, memoranda, manuscripts, manuscript notes, typescripts, and printed materials. Most of the papers concern the bibliographical control of scientific literature with particular emphasis on the development of an information storage and retrieval system for the Olin Mathiessen Chemical Corporation Library. There are letters from librarians and scientists, Olin Mathiessen inter-office memoranda, Fessler's manuscripts, manuscript notes and typescripts, and supporting printed materials published by IBM. There are also mimeograph copies of papers by several other information scientists. Also, Fessler's file of approximately 200 typescripts of his book, record, and cassette reviews on a variety of fiction and non-fiction titles chiefly for Library Journal. In addition there are some course-related materials for the library science classes Fessler taught at Southern Connecticut State College, 1961-1965, including one of his syllabi and some correspondence relating to education for special librarianship. The printed materials include several articles by Fessler and two items inscribed by colleagues to him.
Subjects
Southern Connecticut State College--Faculty.; Olin Mathieson Chemical Corporation.--Library.; International Business Machines Corporation.; Library education.; Information storage and retrieval systems--Science.; Information storage and retrieval systems.; Librarians.; College teachers.; Library journal.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room..
Acquisition
1981 M-81 Fessler, Mrs. Aaron Gift
- Box Contents
  - Biographical Data (includes photocopies of articles on Fessler and a photocopy of a pen-and-ink sketch of him)
  - Book, Record and Cassette Reviews, 1964-1978
  - Information storage and Retrieval - Misc. Conference Papers by Others
  - Library Education for Special Librarianship, 1963-64 (re: Southern Conn. state College)
  - Literature of the Sciences, 1962 (Southern Conn. State College syllabus by Fessler)
  - Olin Mathiessen Chemical Corp. Library - Information storage and Retrieval System
  - Development, 1962-64:
    - Correspondence, Memoranda, Manuscripts, Typescripts, Notes
    - Supporting Materials
  - Philips Laboratories Library, 1959-1960
  - U. S. Senate Scientific Research Study, 1962 (mimeographed memos and news releases)
  - Printed Materials:
    - Articles by Fessler
    - Items Inscribed to Fessler by Others